[Music]
so
welcome living mana church family we are
so happy that you are with us today it
is uh just a great sabbath to worship
together and as always we want to know
where you're worshiping from i you know
before we uh started as as the
intro was starting i saw that we had
some visiting from egypt it's the first
time i've seen egypt so that i was i was
kind of excited i was like oh that's
cool we've had south africa i think
we've had kenya different parts of the
continent of africa but egypt that's
that's really really cool so welcome but
please put in the chat where you're
visiting from uh we're just so happy
that you are worshiping with us today
happy sabbath everyone
happy sabbath we welcome you from uh
wherever you're joining us south africa
wanted to know that there's they're here
today too okay
welcome
uh we're happy to be with you today we
had a
uh rough hectic week this week but uh we
have a lot of people
yeah
praying for us and
and i personally want to say thank you
for the prayer team and the prayer
leaders and all of those who prayed um
at our power wednesday meeting it you
know it really is a blessing you know i
was having um some some health
challenges um related to ms which i'm
pretty transparent about many of you
know um but god is good i'm feeling much
better i'm here i feel great um and so
i'm just so thankful
for the prayers and i just want to
encourage everyone to like i'm glad
you're here on sabbath i'm glad you're
here for mental health mondays and true
health tuesdays
and even for dr pandit on thursday is
really
such a great programming but i'm wanting
to let you know that power wednesdays
are powerful that's what they are our
prayer team is powerful um it's led by
uh brother terry so well and in in all
of the prayer team that he has
surrounded himself with is just truly
truly a blessing i have to say i've put
in their chat like please please pray
it's a silent prayer request you know
over the weeks i've prayed that and i
got it you know they sent an email
saying your silent prayer request is
being prayed over and it was such a
thoughtful detailed email it wasn't just
like an automated response um and so you
if you are wanting prayer please visit
our power wednesdays for prayer put it
in the chat today they are recording
these prayer requests uh brother terry
prays for them during the divine worship
and the team prays for them too if they
don't get to it they pray
over it during the week and so it is
something that you don't want to miss
and and set your phone and alarms to our
different programming i mean if you sign
up on youtube for to be notified it will
do that as well but you can also you
know just remind yourself it's during
the week and maybe you're not used to
awesome prayer or not just prayer
ministry but just different ministries
and and things that we offer during the
week and still you can remind yourself
uh with your alarm that these meetings
are happening and you don't want to miss
them i have to say the true health
tuesday has been a huge
huge blessing um dr schweltz and dr
kenisha reynolds are really they're
bringing the the health knowledge um in
a powerful way so is dr pandit and god
has blessed mental health mondays as
well with dr ricardo white and myself
and so
i just want you to set it in your
calendar and say hey living man at
church is not just live on sabbath doing
great things they are live all
throughout the week and we want you to
participate in that yeah and please be
aware i know we've talked about several
things that we're going to have going on
uh during the week and
one of those things is uh apologetics
yes and uh we have not uh that is we we
just want to let you know that that is
coming
um
we're going to be uh adding some some
new uh
programs i don't want to call it because
this is not a tv station but you know
some uh new material right new new
uh studies throughout the week and um
i think it'll be
uh it'll be a a blessing right uh for
those who continue to watch
it'll be a blessing to share with your
friends and uh just a powerful form of
witnessing so
uh
stay tuned for all of that i love that
you guys are still putting in the chat
where you're worshiping from we have
bakersfield california
i've probably missed a lot because i
haven't been looking at all the chat but
welcome welcome
welcome um we are also going to be
having a meet and greet for our
official church members that have been
uh voted in and there's gonna be these
are gonna happen several times because
they're coming in
in in groups i guess you could say um
and so we're gonna be doing that um and
you'll be getting an email uh from us
from those who are official church
members um that have been voted and
you'll be getting an email uh this week
um it is our goal to do this next week
um but if that doesn't happen it'll
definitely be the week after and you'll
get all that information so be looking
out from an email from your church
living man at church so that you can
yeah i was just gonna say we look
forward to meeting you and uh you'll get
to yeah we'll do it an altar live where
we can have a personal
meeting and greet so that we can get to
know each other um and so as many of the
board members will be there we'll be
there and we look forward to uh getting
to know you guys in a more um personal
way and if might as well say now if
you're wanting to become a member of
living mana church
uh please uh send an email to patrice at
living mana dot live
that should be scrolling across your
screen right now so you can see that
patrice at living mana dot live
she will get your information
and start the ball rolling and and you
can get uh that going and so um yeah we
are just happy that you guys are
want to be here and participate and love
and support the ministry it really does
encourage us each and every
week so and we missed you last week yeah
i mean i know you probably felt like we
were here because we played uh one of
our most popular uh sabbath school
programs back to the basics and we uh we
we've watched and we've seen all your
your comments and everything and how
much you really enjoyed that um and
hopefully you went back because that was
the second one hopefully you went back
and watched the first one and maybe
you've watched some of the others um but
we will be sharing that sporadically at
times but it is a powerful series and uh
brother sebastian did a great job in
this sermon all kinds of stubborn
um all kinds of stuff that was great it
was a great message so um we are we are
happy to be back and we know that last
week um we didn't quite get into the
altar live was not able to go up but
this week it will be so um if we could
put the altar live link in the chat
because i have to say that too i talked
about
uh the power uh wednesday's
altar live is another one of those power
events that um living mana church does i
mean a lot of the prayer warriors are on
there uh brother terry and sister
patrice helped to lead that out and
sometimes brother charles as well and uh
that has also been a blessing just to
hear
what the message and sermon meant to you
what it has done for what it did for you
and also there's prayer there you get to
know each other there you can hear each
other's voices you can see each other's
faces it's all up to you how you want to
interact you can still be in a chat you
don't have to put on your camera you
don't have to talk but it's just nice to
hear people's voices you get to know
them um from all around the world so
after the message it's the ask after
glow is an altar live and after the
message today um we will all uh be on
there and so pastor myers and myself are
always on there as well we try he
comments
but we try
he doesn't comment that much though
but because because you've heard him all
day and you've heard both of us all day
and so we try to we want to hear what
you guys have to say and what's right
and we want to hear from you um but we
are on there listening um and just being
very blessed by your comments and your
prayers and your testimonies it's very
encouraging so i encourage you to join
altar live for the afterglow um after uh
the divine after the message after
divine worship today
and we are continuing our study in the
sanctuary about marriage um and so we
are praying we are
um on the table of showbread and so we
are praying that you will be very
blessed uh by today's study
and for those of you who thought it was
live last week that's okay for you that
was live yeah for you it was live and
that's great
um
parts of the program we're live last
week brother sebastian's sermon was live
brother terry's prayers were live uh
yeah but that's good that's good if you
don't notice that we you should have
noticed though because i did an intro
and i had a bun in my hair and then i
went to straight hair so i mean
and different background i did have the
same t-shirt on that yeah yes and my
t-shirt today i can do all things
through christ hopefully you guys can
read that and
um
kind of the week we went through we
needed like just that type of a message
i can do all things through christ who
strengthens me and he does strengthen us
uh even when you're going through things
he strengthens you all the time but when
you're going through something he comes
even more close and walks with us in a
special way so
i just want to praise god for his love
and his care amen
so with that we're going to pray yes
and we're going to jump into the sabbath
school lesson for today
which is
uh
marriage and the sanctuary marriage and
the sanctuary
and um
we're going to be dealing as we said
with the table of showbread uh we have
dealt previously with the with the labor
with the all star with the ultimate
sacrifice with the labor i'm going to be
tying all those three things in uh as we
talk about the table of showbread today
so let's
let's open it with a word of prayer
heavenly father
uh we thank you lord for
uh the study lord uh that we are um
beginning today lord on the table of
show bread and its relationship to
marriage uh we pray lord that you would
continue to guide us continue to give us
understanding
and uh we pray lord for all the
relationships out there that are uh
needing at one minute needing
reconciliation lord
please lord just guide our thoughts as
our prayer in jesus name
amen and amen amen amen
yes this has been an exciting exciting
study uh so far um just to recap and go
over some things we've talked about uh
the divorce rate in america is 51
51 for christians 54 you know just
regular folks which is a very very high
number
um and so and we just know that um
being a christian and you know have you
know
marrying a christian and having a
christian home doesn't always um
prevent you from from having marital
issues and so this is just
we know that you know
marriages in the church go through the
same things that marriages in the world
go through um we
know
because we're christians we know a
savior who can can help us and help us
to get you know through those very
challenging times but you know because
of
so many different uh factors sometimes
um we don't um
it's enough god is enough
but we don't always choose that and so
that's why the divorce rate um is is so
high and uh we just want to talk about
you know god's way is in the sanctuary
and we can find so many principles um
and practical things we're gonna be
adding definitely the practical things
that you can be doing
to make you know just to help if you're
going through a struggling time in your
marriage to help
you through that if your marriage is
good but you just want to make it better
all of these things
are going to help so
we're definitely looking forward to that
i do want to ask a question because
we've done some things i know um
i think it was the first um
the first series that we did or the
first episode of the marriage and the
sanctuary uh we talked about
saying appreciation to your spouse and i
know that when i ask the second time
many of you just one appreciation a day
just let them know how what you
appreciate about them and many of you
said that you were doing that so i want
you to put one in the chat again if
you're continuing to do that because
your homework was to continue this is
something that goes on throughout your
marriage so i just want to see it one in
the chat if you've been able to do that
and that it's been a blessing so put a
one um and then also we talked about
um
well we're going deeper into
communication today but we were at the
labor we talked about forgiveness um and
we entered into some communication
things there and we just talked about um
having you know you want when you're
talking to your spouse or you want to
bring something up to your spouse having
an easy startup and not a hard startup
like
express you know use your i statements
express how you um are feeling um and
not
tearing down um your spouse with
criticism but just letting them know hey
i feel um and that you know x y and z
instead of tearing them down uh with
criticism and that's usually an easier
startup so you can gonna get the end
result that you want instead of a hard
stop startup meaning coming at them
critically and everything is just going
to make them shut down and you're not
going to get the result that you want at
the end so i just want to see in the
chat how many of you practice that if
you practice
with an easy startup put it to
just waiting hopefully and if you didn't
hear that message go back to the uh
marriage and the sanctuary and the labor
uh but hopefully i'll see some truth
popping up if not we're going deeper
into communication today
so um
let's i see it too praise god praise god
for you
let's
let's start with a recap of the
sanctuary yes
and uh we remember
that
uh
the sanctuary
is
the
structure that god
told the children of israel to build
let them make me sanctuary that i may
dwell
among them
when sin separated man from god right
the answer to that sin problem was in
the sanctuary so that's why the bible
says psalm 77 13 thy way oh god is in
the sanctuary because the sanctuary
shows how
at one minute right
occurs between god and man
it shows how god
wins people
back to himself it shows how god and man
can be one again and so we looked at the
analogy of the church being a symbol of
the bride
and how
you know
god uses the sanctuary
to fix
this broken marriage
to fix this broken
relationship and so if that's the tool
that god uses
to work on
that broken marriage right right to
redeem
his bride yes then
that ought to be the same thing that we
use
as we are you know working on our
marriages seeking at one minute yes
well i just wanted to say because i it
just kind of hit me yesterday and i
think we we did talk about it last night
but we
you know that's really powerful that god
gave us this message and showing us how
he
um is restoring this marriage between
him and his people his church um and
just the world right because he loves
the world and he's trying to restore uh
that connection because
um we don't really have
and i it just really hit me yesterday
for the first time but we just don't
really have examples of
how should i say i'll say it like this
god gave us examples of marriages in the
bible
that
were pretty messed up and broken and
like we can like relate to them like
there's infidelity there's just not
being honest there's just all these
different things i'm like but this but
god gave us the sanctuary to show like
look this is the type of marriage the
way that i relate to the church the way
i treat the church the way i communicate
to the church to my people to you this
is how i this is what i want for your
marriage and so it was like god was
trying to make this as practical as
possible and i feel like we can get you
know encouragement from that um to say
like you know marriage is in the bible i
mean you look at adam and eve even right
so i mean eve
did what she wasn't supposed to do and
adam
followed suit and it just brought all
this
trials and tribulations that we're in
now but
you know we can see like we can relate
that god gave us very relatable
uh people in the bible to say like okay
he is working like he was able to to
give this message of the sanctuary uh to
restore
um them and us and so it it just helps
us to be able to uh relate and know that
we can have hope that god is working
even in these trying marriages that some
of us are in um at times yeah so
let's talk about
the
table of showbread
and actually to set the foundation
um
so we understand that the table of
showbread represents
the word of god
right man shall not live by
bread alone but by every word that
proceeds out of the mouth of god
so
when we get to the top table of
showbread we are looking at god's
mode of communication
to us
right this is the word of god so
this is what we're we're not gonna say
today right we're not gonna
say okay in order to have a
better relationship
um
you know just study your bibles together
right right studying the bible is good
and there listen there are a lot of
marriages a lot of
spouses who know the bible
uh study the bible and yet they're
ending in divorce right
we want to make this very practical yes
the the the word the table of bread
represents communion
it represents your connection with god
right how am i getting close with god
i'm getting close with god by
listening to his communication to me
right and communicating back to him
right
that's how you build a relationship
um
i want you to understand we're also
looking at the altar of incense
as well as the seven branch candlestick
those three articles of furniture were
located in the holy place right
so
as we as we are preparing to go into
those three articles of furniture just
one today but over the next several
weeks we'll be looking at those three
and i want you to understand this
each one of those articles of furniture
now represents
communication
it represents the way we communicate
with each other yes we see jokes yes i'm
sorry to interrupt you i just looked
over and saw one of our
uh
old church members who actually a friend
as well it was one of our youth way back
then at this
joseph godfrey happy sabbath welcome god
bless you i'm so happy to see you i'm
okay we're really excited to see him
here amen okay amen joseph we're going
to connect all right let's connect so
the
the table of showbread
the altar of incense the candlestick all
represent
community it represents relationship
building
right
so in order to do those three
effectively
you first have to
master if you will and i use that word
loosely okay but you first have to
master
the
altar of sacrifice
and the labor you have to learn how to
lay self down you have to learn how to
put things on the altar you have to
learn how to forgive that's the labor
you have to learn how to wash away you
have to learn how to how to
how to generate a new beginning in your
relationship and then
the table of showbread the altar of
incense the seven branch candlestick
which we will see all represent
relationship
building
principles
are going to be effective
but if you haven't first mastered the
the arc of the the altar of sacrifice
laying yourself down right um being
willing to put another above yourself if
you haven't first mastered the labor
forgiveness
your table the way you and your spouse
communicate right is not gonna get
better right
right you're gonna have very little
communication so speaking right now
about the table of showbread we're
focusing in on our verbal
communication with one another that's
what we're talking about and i can tell
you that i've met with
i don't know how many couples but many
many couples
um
for marriage counseling and i can tell
you
honestly all of them come in and say we
want you know you come and say what are
you you know how can i help you and what
are you coming into counseling for and
they want to communicate better right so
communication is
on the radar when there's marriage
issues you know it's on the radar radar
of all uh marriage couples that want to
come in for counseling um but
those previous steps
are where what really makes the
communication better and before you even
get to
the first step the
altar of sacrifice
i mean you're
you're you're there or i should say
before you get there you have to become
aware
that you know there's even an issue or
get to know
um your spouse um and in a way that you
you're you're you're wanting to have
that self-sacrificing love for them but
you have to be aware and to know your
spouse on how to do that
and that is really the first first step
yeah let me i would say this not just to
know your spouse um to get that to get
to know them you do need to get to know
them but a part of that process is
getting to know yourself getting to know
yourself um that we talked about this
morning love languages getting to know
what your spouse's love language is and
to be able to have that proper
communication and what you and your
spouse needs to know what your love
language is yeah
so
unfortunately our our something's going
on with our slides
um and i wanted to show the diagram of
the sanctuary those of you been watching
have seen the diagram but if you
want to you know google it later those
who have just hearing for the sanctuary
for the first time you can you know
well you can i think you could explain
what the sanctuary is for the first
timers because since they can't see it
and then maybe they can google it as
well yeah for a pitcher so yes so
basically
in sanctuary was a was a it was a tent
that had a two compartment
room there was the holy place there was
the most holy place
and then there was the outer court so in
order if you're walking through the
sanctuary
the the place that you enter is called
the outer court that's where the altar
of sacrifice
and the laver is right
the altar sacrifice we pointed out
represents self-sacrificing love laying
oneself on the altar the labor we
pointed out represented forgiveness
represented uh um regeneration
um washing away right and so we talked
about how
these two things are necessary they are
the first things that are required to
build a powerful relationship right so
if i can say this way
we we want a most
holy place relationship in our marriage
yes
but in order to get a most holy place
relationship you have to start at in the
outer court
right the outer you can't jump right
into the most holy place
you have to move you have to master the
outer court learning to lay oneself down
learning to put the other first learning
to to wash away learning to forgive
learning to regenerate go ahead and i
want to say this in like stage one when
you first meet and fall in love and
there's a lot of love and infatuation
there right
you have that
um
that self-sacrificing love for the other
person right we always do this you start
that marriage and relationship like this
if you didn't start like this you would
not have gotten married right you stayed
you started your relationship like this
and you felt like oh i'll do anything
for this person i will you know i love
them so much which you know a lot of
that beginning stage is
infatuation right like i can tell you
after almost 24 years of marriage the
true true love happens
as your marriage grows
and you know you're just feeling like
more connected to this person usually
after you guys have gone through some
things right because the storms are
going to come and the the winds are
going to blow and a lot of time the
storms are coming and coming and the
winds are blowing and it's you know
having you
go like this and you're not as
connected and so
this is what happens in the
communication goes off so it's not like
you haven't
you know i say it's in stages in that
first beginning stage you definitely had
that um
that self-sacrificing love for the other
person but those wins and storms came
and caused you to be like this and so
how do you and then and then you the
communication is off and then now you're
just arguing and bickering and
criticizing and just not being connected
and so we're talking about how to
become reconnected and that
communication be where it should be
because god's teaching us through the
table of showbread um his communication
to us is loving
he's thoughtful he's caring he's
empathetic he's patient that's what his
communication is us those are the
examples that he shows us in his word
that's how he treats his bride
so
at one minute
uh
at one minute is basically i only have
10 fingers if i had 12 fingers
those would be the 12 connecting points
the the six points of the sanctuary were
supposed to connect on the altar of
sacrifice
we're supposed to connect on the labor
we're supposed to connect on the table
of showbread and on the altar of incense
we're supposed to connect on the uh
seven branch candlestick and connect in
the most holy place
true at one minute happens when we're
connecting on all six levels right right
we want to move from a outer court
experience
right to a holy place experience
to a most holy place
experience
that's what we're after in marriage
right so
again
that table of showbread
is where we begin is where we learn how
to
to communicate how we
flow with each other right
so let me ask this question
what is your
what is your communication like
in your marriage is it a river that
means you flow very easily with one
another
right or is it ice
or is it getting to ice
you got you you don't talk too much
right you don't have a lot to talk about
uh you pass yourself you don't need to
put that in the chat i'm not asking you
to respond you know um you can respond
in your mind or however you need to you
don't have to put it here in the chat
but people have said have you just
become really good roommates yeah
right
this is
we need that communication flowing in
the same way god desires communication
to flow between himself
and us right
and so that's what we're focusing on how
can we learn
to communicate with to like talking to
each other
like some
what it what what is it like to be in a
marriage where you don't even like
to communicate with each other we you
have nothing to talk about like that's
just not even basic friendship you know
what i mean right and when i said like
to get a phd in your spouse and to get a
phd in yourself right because a lot of
times
you learn how to deal uh with conflict
from what you learned
as a child growing up from your family
of origin what you saw like uh
it's in a lot of times um our parents
didn't know how to handle conflict i
mean there's a
um a therapy that counselors use that's
um called multi-generational uh theories
and therapy or um transgenerational um
therapy meaning
that
some of the we go like three generations
like i had you know what how did your
parents um
a therapist might say had your parents
um did they did they are they together
are they divorced were they separated
was their drug use was their infidelity
were their mental health issues and
we'll ask those type of questions like
three generations up just to find
patterns um and then the spouse is doing
that in therapy and you're doing that
and you're seeing how um you basically
how you were formed to think um as a
person
um and the patterns that um you have
that you've picked up and that you've
learned and everybody has this because
as children i mean the home that we grow
in we learn how to deal with conflict we
learn how to communicate and
i want to say most of the time it's not
healthy i mean
we have 51 percent of divorce rate um in
our in our country i mean obviously
it's not you know and because we're you
know we're sinful human beings and our
parents are trying to do their best but
you know they had the patterns come down
from them and and then they you know
that's just what they you know that's
what
how they interacted in their marriage a
lot of times it ended up in divorce or
separation or arguments and the children
see all of this and then it passes
it passes down okay now you're here
right and you want to get to know
yourself better and your spouse better
you see that you're having marriage
issues or marital issues and it's just
not where you want it to be
and you want to learn how to stop those
negative patterns so that you're not
passing it down to your children or even
if you you know they might be adults now
so maybe you have but you can um they
can see this real change within you and
you can have this open conversation with
them to even say hey these are some of
the things that
you you and me and your dad or me and
your mom are working on these things we
know this wasn't always the best example
but you know just to have an open
conversation to stop the pattern from
from going forward but it has to start
with you
and your spouse and you have to
be at that place where you want to um
just be aware of enough and enough and
to say okay i want this to change yeah
so if i can explain it this way
if
you don't
kill those old habits and those old
patterns
um
at the altar of sacrifice
then you're gonna bring
that poison right into the t at the
table of showbread right your
communication is going to be right
mingled with
things that are only going to corrupt
the bread
the communication
and so
this is why it becomes important right
to
[Music]
lay those things on the altar of
sacrifice
so that your communication at the table
of showbread
is is pure its it's free-flowing it's
not ice
right
it's a river
it's flowing
um you can talk with one another you can
communicate
there's
no barrier
right there's no barrier that stops the
communication poisons the communication
corrupts the communication
and that's what we're after
so i will say this um
when
one of the best ways i think
to build a strong
uh
communication
uh to build strong communication is to
actually learn
your spouse's love language yes right
that's one
and
learn
what your spouse likes yeah
so think about it in this way
when we become christians right we don't
have a natural
before we became christians we didn't
have a natural love for the word of god
right it wasn't like oh man the bible i
just love it the carnal mind is enmity
against god
but when we decide
look at what he did for me right
now we want to know
what god likes
we want to know what god loves
we want to know what what gets god right
what makes god happy and so what do we
do we try to learn how he communicates
right
and where do we do that at the table of
show bread right we do that by reading
his word
in the same way
we ought to
learn
what is it that my spouse likes what
what is her faith you know what does she
enjoy what does he enjoy what do they
like talking about i want to get because
i'm so building it's building
i like what how dr gottman puts his
building love maps um when you're and
it's building connection yes it's
building connection yeah you're
basically so that you can become like
this again yeah you're trying to get
into the mind of your spouse right what
is it that he or she
likes and how can i connect with them
right on that
what what they like what they are
interested in and so that's that
involves learning one another right
what do we do when we study the bible we
are learning
about god and who got it right and who
god is we ought to be doing the same
with each other right i want to learn
right and and again
get a double phd in your yes
and it's not to say that
you have to necessarily like what your
spouse likes right no that's that's the
whole thing um there's
um just to make this really easy for you
guys it's already it's so easy um it's
learning your uh love language you can
you can just google love language i
don't know if it's oregon.com but you
can take the test
you learn your your spouse's love
language and you learn the you know
characteristics of that and it will make
sense to you because you've been living
with them all you know for how many
years and this is how like what
the way that you can communicate love to
them that they can receive and it and it
helps them and then you do the same and
and they can do that for you and so like
his love language and my love language
are completely different but we know
what they are um and because you're in
this uh relationship and you want to
um have that self-sacrificing love you i
will
i need to and he needs to
speak to me or in actions for me that
is my love language and vice versa for
him and that um
that helps us to stay connected
yeah i like this comment right here
um
uh it's charlotte
uh stanford stanford she says wow pastor
i see how i can contaminate the next
step in the sanctuary i can be in the
wrong place by not completing the
previous step right by holding back or
holding back so
it's
it's a powerful thought because remember
this if
every all the articles of furniture work
together
you start off with one
you don't then jump to the to the next
one and leave the previous one behind
right right each one
builds on the previous one
and so
if i don't
have a working altar of sacrifice right
but i'm moving to these other articles
i'm contaminating everything they
communicate it's not gonna work right
i'm contaminating the communication
the spouse is gonna see right through
that you're not going to talk genuine
right if you don't take that time at the
altar of sacrifice you're not going to
want to learn the love language of your
spouse or get to know them better to be
able to speak their love language so
this connection is going to stay like
this i mean it might come a little
closer but it's not going to be what it
needs to be to protect the marriage from
that 51 divorce rate yeah it's you're
not self-sacrificing or you might stay
in a marriage but be unhappy yeah and
that's not and if you're not willing to
sacrifice self
then that means nah i'm not going to
take the time to get to know what my
father i got things i got to do right
no i don't like what what he likes or
she likes right uh and so it's about me
it's not about my spouse the root
of
conflict is selfishness
and the altar of sacrifice
is
designated
to deal with that issue of selfishness
because it turns you
it teaches you how to focus on others
instead of self right right so
going back to that table of showbread
if we begin to learn
what our spouse
how can we better communicate with our
spouse and how can we get that river
flowing the river may have iced over
right so now it's frozen we don't talk
if we talk we argue right so we try not
to talk at all because we don't want to
argue because we don't want to argue so
there's no communication you get
go back to the altar of sacrifice which
you will see by the time we get to the
candlestick will affect because it's the
other thing that people come in for
communication
and lack of intimacy but the community
if the communication is there if you
know
and i'm jumping ahead to that couple of
furnitures but but if you get to know
your spouse and have this and have that
communication first get to know them
and then the communication
is connected
then um
you will be able that intimacy issue
will not be an issue
and so um
we
are um having um an interruption so but
we are still here so we're not we're
gonna just hold on one second once again
just pause just a second
all right and we are back and i hope i
was i was listening a little bit to the
interruption when i shared that so i
hope that made sense what i the last
thing i said because it's so very
important
your
uh
the communication is going to you can't
really move forward in the other steps
of the furniture but if you have the
communication you're not going to have
issues with your intimacy because you're
going to be it's going to connect you
yeah and it's naturally the intimacy is
naturally going to happen but that's for
two you don't want to miss the one on
the candlesticks so so the candlestick
is about fire
it's about passion right
um
and how that relates
the management when i'm there yet
but just understand that each of these
articles of furniture in the holy place
all deal with building relationships
right
how we connect with our spouses
emotionally
mentally right physically right
and if we can again
deal with our issues at the table of the
at the altar of sacrifice and at the
labor that's where we
we shouldn't try to deal with our issues
in the holy place right the issues are
meant to be dealt with
this is man
okay y'all ready for this i don't know i
feel like you're making it you're going
to get a sermon out of this yeah
the high priest or the priest
could not even
enter into the holy place
without first having
ministered at the altar of sacrifice and
the labor right
he had to come into that place clean yes
and we need to understand if we're not
if we're walking into the holy place
defiled with self defiled with you know
our own
sinful habits and our own sinful ways
we are defiling everything else in the
sanctuary
the holy place is not the place
to deal with your problems
now does that make sense
yeah it no well you're not you're not
going to get there so you and that's no
no it's not you're not going to get
there people go in there you go
corrupted well that's right i shouldn't
say you're not going to go there and go
in there with
a happy you know your marriage is not
going to why is our intimacy not right
right it's not that is not the way that
it's supposed to be why can we
communicate
you haven't dealt
with the labor with the altar of
sacrifice right and so you're walking in
and you are just
totally defiling everything
your your intimacy is defiled your
uh communication is defiled your
emotional intimacy is defiled
all of it is defiled right
and i just want to say uh because kind
of going back to knowing your spouse so
that you can have that communication i
mean uh the love language is definitely
i want somebody to put it in the chat
like the love language so people who are
interested can go take that test to
learn the love languages of their spouse
but another way that has definitely been
a blessing for us and i share this you
cannot come into marriage counseling
with me and we not do
um an enneagram test i don't know how
many of you are familiar with that but
there's nine personality types and i can
say
that if we would have known our
personality types
first 10 years of marriage
mercy would have saved like
all the arguments in the world right it
would have just done so much but when we
understood uh my personality type if
once you if you go and want to just
google enneagram and learn more about it
you can do that you'll see there's the
nine person allen types um and it goes
what actually goes more in depth than
the love language test but i still
encourage you to do the love language
test
and do the enneagram test because uh it
like it just makes it easier when we
don't see eye to eye and there's caught
and there's a conflict you know trying
to enter into our space
like the way i i know
who he is better i understand where he's
where he's coming from and it's not and
sometimes we don't understand our
spouses um and then we our feelings get
hurt or there's so much misunderstanding
just because you don't really know them
the way that you need to know them um
and it is just helps in our marriage
like we can just joke about it sometimes
okay my number is an eight his number is
a nine totally different personality
types there's a healthy version there's
an unhealthy version um and of that
personality type so you're getting to
know yourself as well which is so very
important and we can just joke and i'll
be like okay that's your
nine side of you you know feeling that
way okay i get it he knows that my aide
is going to respond a little bit
differently and we understand it better
and i can tell you that it just makes a
world of difference in your marriage
really getting to know
uh because god created us all different
um and even when you're in you can have
the same person there's there's millions
of eights and nines and twos and threes
but even in those numbers you're still
different like you're unique to who you
are like god is a creative god
and so
it is just so important for your spouse
and for yourself to know who you are
yeah
i want to just just building on that
thought and
and connecting with what we just shared
before
think about and i want to take this back
to the altar of sacrifice
think about how many
marriages
have ended
right
because of
infidelity because of
uh you know whatever it might be
because someone
failed
at the altar of sacrifice
right
right right they failed to
consider
spouse first they failed to consider
family first they failed to consider all
they were thinking about was themselves
like
they defiled themselves right and so
what happens is
when we when we don't match that altar
of sacrifice as i said earlier
and you're trying to dwell in the holy
place all you're doing
is defiling
defiling every article of furniture to
the point where well why can't we
communicate why can't you know why are
we not intimate why and all these things
will have an effect and basically just
at one minute can happen right and when
that one man can't happen the result is
divorce
right right
um
and we can do a whole nother series just
on
dating yes
yes because i want you to understand
that
if we look at those articles of
furniture you got the outer core we will
do a whole another series on dating yeah
you have the outer court you have the
holy place you have the most holy place
the most holy place
is where you and your you and the person
you're dating are now standing at the
altar this is under the context of
dating now right right
in dating the end result is ah
we are now
at the most holy place
where at one minute
occurs
how do i know the right person
to join myself with
well
do we connect at the altar of sacrifice
right right do we connect at the labor
right and
now you're looking at a totally
different you know approach
but
once you get to that most holy place in
the marriage
we're married now
now you got a whole new sanctuary thing
to go through because now it's like okay
in the context of marriage
i got to learn to lay self down
i told my spouse you know before we got
married oh i'll do anything for you but
now we're married right now we're in the
at one men phase can i maintain
uh
the altar of sacrifice can we have a
working altar of sacrifice in our home
can we have a working labor in our home
and again the reason why so many homes
are destroyed is because
these articles of furniture aren't
working right
right they aren't there's no connection
on these articles and so again they end
up defiled
and we end up separated from god
so
remember
if you remember nothing else because we
said we said a whole lot
deal with the problems
in the outer court yes
yes
do not bring the problems
into the holy place they're not supposed
to be there the holy place is for
totally different purpose the holy place
is for connection
deal
with the issues and so now you can
understand every issue that i have
has to do
with me either not willing to lay myself
down or me not willing to forgive me not
willing to wash away me not willing to
regenerate to start anew right
everything and you know for that in that
case we could spend so much time just in
just in understanding the outer court
and how it relates and you know to our
relationship
we've got to
we've got to deal with our issues there
so that
when we get into the holy place
everything
flows
smoothly right you know the series is so
important um because you know what did
satan attack in the garden right like
marriage marriage and he does not want
he wants our marriages to be higher than
the world 51 i mean a percent higher
than
those who don't necessarily claim to
even know god right but he wants he
wants their marriages to fail too and
because he knows how much hurt it brings
to us as individuals but what it does to
our children what it does to our
families and he does not
and he just wants like i was talking
about he wants those generational
patterns to continue
um because it just makes it you know
when your marriage is in a situation
when you're not happy in your marriage
it's it's hard to
just have a relationship with god to you
know you can go through the the motions
but have to have a real relationship
with god because you're just so unhappy
uh in the situation and in your life and
you don't have that peace and so and
that's what satan wants and so that's
why
we uh are so committed to talking about
this topic and giving as much
helpful
tools and of course bible principles to
be able to help
your marriages um and because it's so
very important because this is what
satan is attacking
that he is that he is yes and we can see
it again in the numbers i mean 51 half
of marriages is really a high number um
you know
it's half that's a lot that's a lot you
spend so much money on a wedding into a
beautiful and beautiful pictures and all
that and then you know
five ten i mean nowadays if you're
making it five if you're making it ten
years you're doing wow and some people
are just you know you're making it to
those times but you're unhappy the last
five and then it just ends up um in
divorce and
and so again that is uh satan's goal but
god's way is in the sanctuary and he has
uh
made made a way um and so this is what
we're trying to show uh through the
sanctuary because it's just so very
important and it's he god is so
practical like he cares
um and that's why the bible's so amazing
because we did the sanctuary through
anger now we're doing it through
marriage and
we will find other ways to do it and
because there's so many principles there
to learn because i mean you can't you
can't exhaust god's word
um
you just can't yeah
so
i think in recapping
um
we're understanding the importance of
the table of showbread
and we're understanding that
we're not dealing if we have bad
communication we're not dealing with it
at the table of children
we're dealing with it in the outer court
we want our communication to be good we
want our communication to flow to not be
ice
and so
i think the walk away from this is
if i'm struggling
help me to go back
get out of the holy place
go back to the to the outer court and
let's figure out what am i not laying
down right right what am i missing here
what in me what thing from my childhood
what thing from my parents or their
parents parents have i brought into the
holy place and we are all bringing
something and it is not one person we
were both we are both everybody is
raised by somebody and if you're not
raised by anybody you're still
learning things um and so and it's not
one person's fault i haven't really been
following the chat very closely but i'm
seeing some things about women and men
i'm not surely have you been reading it
i don't know no no i haven't okay just
it is not
um and i'm not quite i i you know well
i'm gonna comment on it because i just
picked up on a few things but it is not
one person it's not a man's issue or a
woman's issue it is
both of our issues that bring issues to
a marriage that cause uh cause problems
um
and so at one minute takes two it takes
two it takes two
so
uh to blame the wife or to blame the
spouse you know your goal is to
to start at that altar of sacrifice and
have that um
self-sacrificing love to get to know
your spouse um in a way so that you can
stay connected if you're not connected
reconnect and have that communication at
the table of showbread that you need and
moving forward we will see that a lot of
the issues that people bring into the
um
into those next articles of furniture
are
because they didn't do the previous um
articles of furniture and so that's why
the communication is bad yeah and let me
let me say this because i saw a comment
a little bit earlier which
really brought this picture to my mind
how sometimes we can be at different
levels
and
think about that altar of sacrifice why
is it the first level
like you know if we're in a situation
where
you have a child
a spouse a loved one and let's just say
something dramatic happens where they
get injured
you have the chance to either
run to save your own life or pick them
up
and move as fast as they can move right
you're not moving faster than they can
move you're moving as fast as they can
move
that takes self-sacrifice right
and and think of it in this way
sometimes
a spouse may be wounded
and not even realize
right and they they might
they might not be you might be ready to
jump into the most holy place you might
be ready to
but they're not there yet right it takes
that patience that perseverance that
self-sacrificing love
to
try to move with your spouse
right no faster than they can move right
and and so that in itself is an act of
of self-sacrifice it is necessary
to have that self-sacrificing love to do
something like that
again the the situations may vary so i'm
not saying you know again this is not
we're not talking about
spousal abuse right yeah or things of
that nature we're talking
we're talking about when there's yeah
when there's physical abuse yeah that's
not what we're we're speaking about
physical abuse needs to be
dealt with in a serious manner and i you
know i suggest you know if you're in
that situation have to do these
disclaimers all the time but if you're
in that situation
there's mental health professionals that
can help you
get assistance there's there's shelters
um for you there's women shelters family
shelters that can assist in every
community that can assist um in these
situations um and so
it's
you know god wants you to be protected
and it's not okay for somebody to
violate your
your
physical health or emotional health and
so
it's important to get assistance if
that's the situation you are in yeah and
now i'm really thinking about this this
uh dating thing and somebody just
mentioned courtship
and i thought about the outer court with
courtship i just
kind of made that mental connection
and
everybody this is the partnership
anymore yeah yeah but this is the thing
is like if
if the person that you're considering
marrying
is not
demonstrating
that outer court quality right
willing to lay self down
uh
forgiving
those attributes those kind of
attributes
um
yeah you know again this is we're kind
of jumping into dating but yeah be
careful
yes because those attributes
on that yeah they will spill out into
the actual marriage so
uh but again and really and really going
just back to getting to know really you
want to get to know the person and we
are going to dating courtship but i
don't care no
but dating the person the person you're
dating this is when you really should
learn if you're if you're serious and
you feel like this is this person that
you're dating is marriage material and
this is you feel like god is leading you
uh it is that that time that you need to
learn their love i mean it would be
wonderful if at that time you learned
their love language
if you get to know them get your phd in
them understand their personality type
it is so very important um it will
assist you
in um the marriage a great deal you will
be ahead of the game you will be ahead
of the game you won't be like 10 years
in like we did and like wish
we would have you know had that type of
knowledge or had somebody counsel us to
say we did have premarital counseling
but we didn't get that information um if
you know it just would have had that
information it would have helped so much
but really that that courtship stage is
really where you you you should do that
but that is good because you can do it
within the marriage too you might go
through some you will go through some
valleys but um you can come out of them
you can come back up to the mountain and
be reconnected even if that doesn't
happen in courtship amen or in your
dating time that's what it really is
called now dating time
well yes we could go on and talk about
this for hours and hours and hours and
i'm sure that many people would like to
still hear about it for hours and hours
and hours just knowing that the divorce
rate is at 51 but
we that's why there's always next week
so we will continue and we'll always be
going back and covering some of those
other
um articles of furniture just like today
we were you know on the table of
showbread talking about communication
but we were able to just continue to
build on some of these other pieces of
furniture and so we're going to continue
to do that so we just praise god that
you were here and your comments and
participating you have homework so i
only had one two i think it was rick
maybe there was another one so if i
missed you i'm sorry because i'm not
always completely focused on the chat
but i saw rick said he did he tried the
uh god bless you rick he tried to do the
easy startup when he had to communicate
and you're doing an easy startup with
your spouse when you know you're going
to talk interrupt for a second yes
because i do it all the time but of
course this this this course you think
is going to be fun this dating thing i
just want to okay someone said uh it is
it is important to do a background check
because some people pretend in courtship
this is true i don't know about the
background at all yeah i mean you know
this is what i mean well
the sanctuary is the background check
right the sanctuary is the background
check
it's true i mean they're showing you
their because i yeah it's hard to
pretend
true self-sacrificing love it's hard to
pretend yeah um
true forgiveness but but it but it
happens so yeah but i get the point we
get the point you do need to be you need
to be thorough yeah that's project yeah
background check that's your back
project all right so um now i'm trying
to remember what i was saying um
oh yes your homework so
um again you're wanting to do
when you're wanting to talk to your
spouse and you know it's going to be
something that usually would cause an
argument or it wouldn't go well
um and you know there's conflict there
you want to
you want to approach them with an easy
startup you know just say you know how
you're feeling not attacking them not
tearing them down not criticizing them
to say you know i feel
again x y and z i feel a little hurt
today might you know because of you know
this situation that happened and just
softly
going into the conversation and
expressing how you feel versus a hard
startup again that's just gonna shut
them down
i mean just going to shut them down and
raise that wall of resentment and
defensiveness and you're just not going
to have the end result that you want so
if you want to get what you want have a
soft startup and i want you to practice
that this week uh with your spouse
approach them in a different way
that's one homework the second homework
we're just still building um is to show
up and if your husband and wife watching
i hope couples together watching today
um to
say one thing that you appreciate about
your spouse each and every day again you
can say it verbally you can text it
however you feel comfortable and so that
is your homework and then when we come
back next week i want to see a whole
bunch of ones and a whole bunch of twos
that actually got to do that and if you
have any little testimony you can put it
in the chat too amen so
yes we look forward to continuing our
study and discussion next week
so we uh we thank you guys for joining
us uh for cyber school now please
uh we're gonna go into our uh divine
worship and we want you to share share
this link
um share the link i should have said
this earlier but share the link on your
social media let everyone know that
you're here
with us also follow us on instagram at
my living manna that's very important
our instagram is growing so praise god
but continue and when you
when you follow us when you see us post
something which is several times a week
share it to your story because that gets
the word out even more so we have to be
very social uh media savvy here all of
us have to do that so that helps to get
the word out but just share on your um
on your social media that right now um
we're that you're in church with living
mana church and that the actual church
service is beginning and if they missed
our marriage talk for you have to say
hey you got to go back and watch the
replay
so you are our virtual
uh lay bible workers when you do that so
we praise god for that and uh please
stay tuned for the sermon because uh
it's it's gonna be
extremely eye-opening just start sharing
with people now uh the title of the
message is called the march on the
capitol
um
y'all are not going to want to know what
you think and it's yes it's never what
you think it's never what you think
just just just know that okay
it's never what you think
um
so
put your prayer request in the chat
because the prayer warriors are out
there they're on they're taking your
prayer requests brother terry's um
he's observing it as well and so he will
um be praying over some of these
requests as well during the divine
worship now let me let me mention this
as well and i don't know if we have the
link for this ready but um
we are preparing to launch our seven
week um
uh character
training
program character training workout and
so if you want to get a hold of this pdf
all you need to do
is sign is uh uh click on the link and i
don't know if we can put the link up
i don't know if we're ready to do that
right now if we don't put it up in this
segment we will put it up in the
following segment
um but click on the link so that we can
get your email address and you will get
that pdf we're going to launch it here
over the next several days so
um
just uh
be aware of that many of you have been
asking about wanting to be a part of
that seven week training
uh you can do this individually you can
do this in a small group
but
it is designed
for you
to transform your character that's the
goal of the seven week training program
uh so uh with that said i don't i i
don't see the link up i don't think we
have put the link in but we'll put it up
by the fireworks show yeah service yeah
all right would you like to pray for us
okay all right dear heavenly father lord
thank you so much uh for this time that
we got to talk about such a a real issue
um that faces our christian homes all
homes all marriages are being attacked
lord and everyone can grow
from this information and so i just pray
that um it has touched um
everyone all of us if they if they are
struggling in marriage that they're
seeing that there's hope if their
marriage is good but they want to
improve it they see that that is
possible and so lord i just pray that
this information will be taken to heart
and will
just change marriages all around the
world as those who are viewing this
information
we ask that you will just the holy
spirit will just continue to be with us
as we continue to worship
as we go through the divine worship
service and we just thank you for your
sabbath and your answered prayers our
answered prayers lord um just thank you
for being a good loving god in jesus
name amen amen
what name could contain such a glory
[Music]
in the cool breezes of eden
brought from the infant earth
one arose
the voice of his creator speaking his
identity to life
adam
man
and his heaven waded short with bread
the creator spoke yet another
eve
mother of all the living
so it was with abraham named in the
promise as the father of nation
peter the rock upon which the church
would stand
the name called to life the destiny
within the name set the stage for all
that was to come
and unto us a child was born
and what name could contain his glory
for he was mighty god as the universe
gasped into being flinging rays of light
from his presence to pierce the void to
shatter the shadows to a tapestry of
color
and he is mighty god shattering our
darkness revealing our light
he was everlasting father when orphaned
israel needed a father's touch
when we with grief-stricken cheeks need
the embrace of one who never leaves
when we have lost our way to dark
horizons it is our